[Applause]
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software supercar welcome to software
engineering radio it's a pleasure to
have you hey thank you Jeff pleasure to
speak to you as well and thanks for
inviting ya so today we're mainly gonna
be talking about nodejs and the the
platform and the ecosystem so where you
start off by talking about what is no
js' yeah so Jeff if you look at it
javascript has existed in the browser
world for an almost a decade now more
than a decade and all of a sudden the
power of JavaScript was ported over to
the server side instead of just making
it run on the client side in the browser
and server side javascript is
essentially what is now known as nodejs
and this technology stack is helping
power the transformation for API is
mobile and IOT applications today and
what do you mean by the power of
JavaScript all right so if you look at
it right like originally server-side
applications were built in Java or.net
variety of thread based technologies
right and that was the way to scale
applications and so very much you were
stacking those aspects when JavaScript
came to the back-end all of a sudden
people realized that we can have
JavaScript at both ends of both on the
server side as well as on the client
side and what this lets us do is build
what we call as isomorphic JavaScript
applications and I'll talk about that in
a little bit more detail but what's
happening in today's world is you know
if you look back let's say you know 10
years right we were building web pages
we are rendering HTML and today the
world has changed drastically
we are coding api's not apps so that's
why you'll see the terminology that it's
an API economy rather than being an app
economy and those API is need to be
lightweight and those API is need to be
served from the backend as rest rather
if you can have the power of serving
them in JSON the consumption of those
API is on the front side which is also
running JavaScript becomes extremely
easy and nodejs is the technology which
is helping you deliver these lightweight
api's rendered as json in an extremely
high scale manner which means the needs
of concurrency needs of mobile
applications IOT applications so that's
what I mean by transformation and you
know I can talk about that more from an
architecture person so to boil some of
that down as I understand what you said
is much of the power of node
specifically as a JavaScript back-end is
basically treating JSON as a first-class
object very correct very correct and if
you look at it people used to joke about
having a JSON database right and all of
a sudden MongoDB merged and you know you
had variety of data stores which can let
you persist JSON right so on the front
end if you're recording in JavaScript
you have you can process JSON if you are
on the middleware which essentially is
no js' you can generate JSON and on the
backend with you now if you have a
MongoDB type store you can persist JSON
so now you essentially have what we call
as full stack JavaScript stacks evolving
very similar to how a lamp stack had
evolved a few years back interesting
yeah because because you think about the
you know if you if you have to build
like a java application compared to
building an application in in node it's
funny because you know in a java
application you'll maybe you would have
to use jackson to parse the json objects
that come in and this is actually like a
big it's iconic of like a big annoyance
you know you have to use this annoying
kind of clergy interface to get to the
heart of your JSON objects and if you're
if you're working a node for example
it's it's just so much it's just so much
easier it kind of comes out of the box
exactly it's a you know it's a big in
method okay you can simply do json dot
get and you can essentially get access
to the entire json object without having
to go through the pain of d
serialization parsing extracting out
then you know again converting it into
another protocol and sending it over the
wire right okay and so to separate that
aspect of a beneficial component of node
there's also the single threaded event
loop aspect which is like which is c it
strikes me as a totally different aspect
of the ease of programming in node so
III want to stress the single threaded
event loop aspect of node pretty early
on the conversation and because i think
we'll need to keep coming back to it
because i i've been hearing about node
for years and but it's taken me a while
to appreciate the kind of simplicity and
the effectiveness of it beyond just the
fact that it's JSON so soto or that you
can use JSON like i said previously so
explain this the single threaded event
loop aspect yes so think about it this
way right normally if you you know
there's a big confusion about hey you
know node is single threaded is that
good as that bad right and is this a
bottleneck in scaling node.js
applications by itself i see it as a
great advantage so if you look at the
origin of asynchronous programming right
if you go back to this this has been
done in operating systems way back in
you know windows as well and original
you know unix based handling and then
you saw the emergence of middleware
classic middleware but you say we use
the unix based model is multi-threaded
it is but if you look at how we were
dealing with POSIX threads on the UNIX
systems right there was some kind of
Orchestrator which we is dealing with
all the operating system threads and
delegating tasks for i/o operations okay
and if you take the same model over to
classic middleware even in Java land
right you had message driven beans and
then you know classic middleware like
the tip goes and all those emerged which
were traditionally doing asynchronous
message driven programming so you are
not really and that allowed them to
scale that based on events at an
extremely high scale model right so
coming back to the single thread in
nature of it the way it works is think
about it this way right you have a set
of requests coming in and event loop is
essentially a post master or an
Orchestrator process the event loop
itself runs single threaded but it goes
and accepts all these requests
simultaneously but it does not go and
take over the execution of the requests
it's essentially a delegator what it
does it picks up an operating system
thread and passes of the delegation of
the requests in terms of i/o operations
to that operating system if in the UNIX
land this could be a simple POSIX thread
and so a request comes in from a user
perspective the event loop returns what
is called as a pointer which is
essentially callback and then the
operating system thread picks it up does
the back end i/o processing serves the
response back however the event loop
remembers the route the memory pointer
that it used for the callback so because
it keeps in memory all these routes it
can then attach the appropriate are your
response back to the originating request
however while it's doing this you know
when it gets a request fending off back
to the POSIX thread it does not actually
win it for that request to come complete
it just keeps moving on right so first
request comes in delegation next next
next and so on right
so it's obviously you know it does not
have that traditional waiting bottleneck
that we encountered in a Java world or a
dotnet or a rather thread based world I
myself used to be a Java Architect for
about 1314 years and classically the way
we scale
amps or CLR systems was we operated off
at Red Bull
so we'll say hey you know what let's
spin up 1024 threads and when every
request comes in it essentially consumes
a thread and that thread has to make a
back-end IO operation and while that eye
operation completes that thread is
waiting now if you had a lightning-fast
back end which would respond in a
nanosecond
you are all cool you'll never run out of
you know you'll never consume all your
thread pool ever because you know the as
soon as the operation is done the thread
is returned back in the pool however the
fact is in production grade systems back
end operations or disk operations are
generally slow and when you do this your
threads are consumed for that time when
you are doing that IO operation and what
happens is if you have huge concurrency
on the front end which now in the new
world you will see with mobile apps
right because mobile apps you are
getting a lot of tiny events you're not
really serving up webpages you have
things like infinite scroll going on and
you are getting event based data or IOT
sensor based apps these are requesting
event based data so you have huge
concurrency but very tiny fragments of
data the server or the JVM or the CLR
won't know the difference between an
event which is an HTML page or an event
which is a sensor event it still treats
it as a single thread so what happens is
this can easily fill up your thread pool
and your threads will start waiting this
is the essential problem that node.js is
solving due to the entire asynchronous
way of processing so I think that was a
great explanation and just to drill on
that a little bit more so that our
listeners really understand maybe you
could talk in a little more specific
detail about an example of i/o that like
a typical example of i/o that that node
would be a good solution for so because
as I understand the i/o problem was
basically the impetus for Ryan Dahl
creating node correct so so what would
be those I mean you talked about
infinite scroll you think we could we
could use
as an example or whatever you think is a
good example yeah so if you are
traditionally dealing with I or we are
here let's define what is IO force right
what is an i/o operation really mean to
note okay so we all talk about the event
loop being single threaded
however for memory and network
operations it is actually multi-threaded
right so it actually uses the thread
pool of the operating system threads to
do those i/o operations now IO is
anything that is attached to a callback
so when you get a request in node and
what node gives you is a callback and
that callback is supposed to do an i/o
operation for you okay and that could be
a database call it could be as simple as
consumable back-end rest call it could
be writing a file to disk or maybe the
reading from disk right it could be a
disk operation as well or it could be
anything to do with memory segmentation
right so even if you look at garbage
collection the way it works you know
when you actually instantiate new
objects in memory you have to talk
directly with the RAM right however you
know as your objects exit the scope
execution scope of your applications
then you know the garbage collector
takes over and you know it goes and
cleans up your memory but the
application is no longer dealing
directly with the RAM we now push the
first allocation of the objects right so
you are in a way these are all general
IO operations so if I take a use case or
what is an application I will tell you
first what are the application people
are building in node so node I would say
is highly optimal for building let's say
a web RTC application right so these are
we see them a lot where you are looking
at you know web ID say web RTC yeah web
RTC is that stand for there's a
real-time web real-time communication or
real-time yeah so if you're looking at
things like you know building a face bus
yeah so if you're looking at platforms
like talk box you know you name it right
like not not everything in Google
hangout it is you know was built or node
but a lot of newer players right who are
loading web RTC as a platform for
delivering video and voice content are
using node right so that's one good use
case the gaming industry is using node
extensively because again it's the same
use case of real-time communication
using WebSockets we know for
communication for end-to-end or peer to
peer communication so okay so just just
to clarify to give a higher level
picture of how this might look is like
the client or the user has you know he's
got his mobile device he's got some chat
application open basically and every
time he sends a message to his friend
that chat message hits the server and
then the server receives that message
we'll say it's a restful request and
then that hits the node stack right on
the server side that is correct however
if you could even implement the
server-side logic itself in node and if
you were able to share the client and
the server side models somehow the state
of it you will be cutting down a lot of
latency along the wire so it really
makes it so that's where you will see
node both on the front end as well as in
the back end in case of let's say gaming
type industries okay so it's essentially
you know your speed of execution but I
would say these are some use cases you
know which I've seen different people
use inevitably some of them are using
node for let's say screen scraping and
single page apps as well but if you
really look at the number one use case
that I would say 80 to 90% of the
industry is using for node.js that is to
build api's okay and when we talk about
api's these api's are powering mobile
and when we say let's take an example of
oh I have a mobile application if I have
a big company enterprise and I wanted to
have like claim data you know let's talk
old-school right we always know the use
cases about new-school
you know high-tech innovative companies
but is not going to really help the
mainstream enterprise saying hey I have
this business data in a back-end system
which is essentially
I had written an service-oriented
architecture on the back end right and I
was rendering soap to all these web
application and web services which were
written in Java or.net right now those
soap requests used to take me you know
let's say two seconds three seconds four
seconds to render and I was still okay
with them right my webpages you know I
could render static images earlier and
then when the real payload came in I
would then go ahead and you know render
up a web page in two seconds and user
won't complain now all of a sudden that
was my online sales that's why I handle
online sales in my enterprise now my CMO
is asking me hey can you give me mobile
sales right so my challenge has that
okay I can go and write a native native
iOS or app or an android app now I need
to get these app consume the same soap
messages right from the backend but
again scale at a very high level because
you know on mobile my mobile traffic is
growing my web traffic is shrinking so
how do I do that right so what node has
essentially become is a glue integrating
all these legacy and new tech sit back
and systems with newer front ends like
mobile what we now call as the front
edge right with your various interfaces
so how does not do that so node
essentially helps you build lightweight
api's we're originally used to compose
api's but node is taking it in a
different way of saying decompose api's
it so break down your soul maybe I can
talk directly with the database maybe
you are storing you need to store this
data in JSON in MongoDB and I can
consume those JSON or that database
table or a method within that soup
operation essentially as a model and
this model can I can represent that in
JavaScript within the load middleware I
can apply all schema validation around
that and you will see the emergence of
automatic api's REST API generation
using open source projects like swagger
yeah yeah she's done real quick so do
you think that node is actually is there
something like
fundamental to writing server-side
JavaScript that makes this makes
building this interface that's a glue
that holds everything together is there
something special about JavaScript or is
it just the fact that it happened to be
that we're writing server-side
JavaScript right now and also we have
this we have lots of new models for
backends and since no js' is kind of
this just a new framework it happens to
be that people are writing stuff for it
that that makes it useful do you see the
root of what I'm asking like I'm you
know maybe we're maybe we're not using
the old systems basically because they
have they've developed so much cruft but
there's not and then there's not
anything particularly special about
nodejs except that it's the thing that
is new right now therefore it's the
easiest and the freshest and might as
well evolve node well I don't say that's
the use case right I would say three
things right about node being on the
JavaScript is first is you are now being
able to isomorphic we build applications
right not that node is just new it's
almost been five years now but that
option curve is just growing
exponentially the second is it helps
solve concurrency that's the number one
problem
okay due to the non blocking mode of
working third is it's essentially
helping me build full stack JavaScript
applications is that mano that's monocot
programming is that smaller block
programming I will come to that because
you know that's another pattern that we
are seeing emerging and the fourth is
that the node is essentially from a
performance perspective there are you
know discussions around this but there
is a specific scientific logic why node
if you in the world the best way can
achieve much higher performance than
traditional thread base technologies
right so those are the four drivers and
if you may I can you know touch upon
each of those sure so let's talk about
you know we talked about in event loops
and you know asynchronous i/o right and
that's essentially what is help you
propel it's helping you can support
concurrency at a much higher level right
and this concurrency this
is in mobile session IOT sensor-based
sessions and you'll note is exactly
tuned to you know handle it because you
know it does not have the limitation of
the thread pool right it can almost
theoretically scale infinitely as long
as sockets are available to handle that
yeah so the second thing I was talking
about is essentially polyglot
programming right but before I go that
let's look at even the runtime so we
said okay you know asynchronous is good
but what makes node also faster in terms
of performance is that it's not really
compiled pre compiled code or it's not
pre interpreted code right so like if
you look at a traditional JVM you are
essentially compiling everything
beforehand into byte code okay and if
you're looking at interpreted programs
you know the same thing was happening
but you are essentially doing runtime
interpretation node users intentionally
runtime compilation
okay now or what we do also call as JIT
pattern and this is another essence of
whites you know much faster a much
lighter I would rather say then a fact
come you know pre-compile app ok and we
will talk about more detail in you know
how v8 evolved and you know what's under
the line which is making this go faster
but the third pattern we were talking
about was polyglot programming so what
happens is think about angular write
angular as MVC on the front end or any
other you know you could be using back
born marionette you know you you got
your MVC choices on the front end and
node itself is also helping you do
embassy in a way right now the models
that you are creating if you can share
that model over the wire this both the
state and the spec with the front end
then what you can do is you can achieve
use cases like offline sync right so
think about this this way you know in
the java days there was a technology
called as jax-rs
which help you do remoting you know
access the server side the models on the
client without actually having to write
too much stubby so new protocols have
emerged and new tools have emerged you
might have heard about packages like
browserify which are essentially letting
you run server-side JavaScript code on
the client side job as
sighs JavaScript right so you can
actually browserify your entire node.js
application the second one we also had
strong loop wrote a protocol called as
from remoting which essentially helps
you share that model so you can number
because that sounds like remarkable if
you can essentially put the server in
the browser you could you could you die
and I've actually heard people talking
about browserify but I haven't like
looked into what that is so - yeah but
that sounds like pretty game-changing so
what is that oh it is it is so think
about it this way right I created some
data models on the server side in
node.js right those are my data models
and those data models if you look at
browserify you can essentially say all
these are javascript models and they
have to go under some directory
structure it basically pick up like
create a browser bundle if you're using
a tool like browserify
you can create the entire browser bundle
of those models and use that bundle
remotely in your angular application so
in its kind of an sdk right you have to
drop that in ins + 3 au s-- that browser
bundle but what that gives you gives you
a remote route and if you are using a
protocol like strong remoting you can do
this even without browserify but it
gives you a way to access over the wire
the state of that model and share that
model representation on the front-end
MVC so for example think about it this
way the same model exists on both client
and the server and they are continuously
trying to sync over the wire okay
client-side changes it goes and syncs
the changes to the server side and
server side changes its send pushes it
out to the client side so there's always
or two-way sync going on okay and it's
not really rocket science per se how
this is done with this essentially
replication right are you've maintained
two copies of exactly the same model on
book site now if but this is it sounds
so heretical compared to I mean you're
supposed to keep the front end kind of
lightweight right I mean you you're not
I mean traditionally right this is like
this is like a separation of church and
state kind of thing like you don't want
you don't want to just say
we're gonna give the browser free rein
we're gonna give the browser like as
much memory as it needs I mean is this
is this just like a fundamental change
based on like how much memory that we're
giving the browser or no no no no so you
know I don't want to absolutely make the
front end fact right okay and so I'm not
going to put any of my controller or my
viewer viewing or any of the wiring
logic onto the front end what I'm going
to do is whatever models that I
generated my data models only those data
model specs I will and these are like
essentially JSON files right each model
can be represented as a JSON object only
those JSON objects I will package and
share with the client-side I think so in
browserify you can say okay go and just
look up a directory structure if I keep
my JSON objects in a particular
directory structure you can just
specifically pick up only the models and
not consume anything else okay if you
use something like strong remoting it
essentially helps you define the remote
routes and on the angular side you can
be saying okay this model I'm going to
access it local it's present under this
route or when I'm essentially 70 is
setting up routing on the angular app I
can also say oh use a remote route right
and the remote route you know the model
is exact same model is present there now
what happens is for storage right
obviously you need to keep this in sync
so you need some kind of client storage
right for JavaScript it is easy because
we had strong to what we ended up doing
and even like IDs you know CouchDB guys
all Couchbase whereas actually also did
the same is they implemented what they
call as object storage into the HTML
local 5 browser okay so that's where the
models you have saved every time you
know there is an event now if you get
offline due to any chance the model is
still saved into the html5 browser
storage and when you get online because
it's supposed to sync real time the
model will now try to get synced on the
server side however if you made any
changes on the server side or on the
client side these two
models aren't in sync anymore so when
you try to resync over a network
connection then you can you will have
conflict right because the models are
not interesting anymore so now you can
also do conflict management on the
server side oh whether do you want to
keep the server side models do you want
to persist the client side models or do
you want to overwrite them is it based
on timestamp is it based on the master
copy or the slave copy so you know these
type of implementations have recently
started coming in and I call this what
we call as isomorphic Jas they are
powering isomorphic JavaScript
applications could you give a broad
definition for fir isomorphic JavaScript
applications I would say isomorphic
JavaScript applications are those apps
which have their own control and viewing
logic either on the client side on the
server side but this do share the state
and the specification of the models
between the client and server
interesting okay so and then to
regurgitate your explanation of
browserify as a in a blur of isomorphic
JavaScript applications my understanding
of how you Illustrated that was you have
basically a directory structure on the
client side and you also try to have
that that directory structure in sync on
the on the server side and you
constantly have a synchronization going
so if you have if you have some sort of
some some sort of client client
application where you know let's say
you're playing a game in the browser for
example and you've got all these objects
in the game that are constantly being
updated
you know browserify would work well
because you can look at these different
game objects as things that are things
that are in our directory structure
constantly getting updated and you just
constantly cinq-cinq the - is that an
accurate description correct you are
essentially syncing JSON objects across
the wire right and you know whatever it
is and you know they are not insane
then you'll have to apply some sort of
set of programmatic rules to manage the
conflict either on the client side
mercilessly fascinating okay so to bring
that back to how node plays a big role
here do you do you just have I mean
there's no just constantly is like where
would its nodes a big role here is it
being the the application that's that's
syncing these two and it's maybe just
iterating constantly it like is the
single is the single thread of job of
node just iterating through this
directory structure making sure things
are synchronized no node is essentially
going to be your runtime platform for
helping you do a you know do a modeling
on the server side in JavaScript right
because if you don't do this in
JavaScript on the server side how else
are you going to you know keep persist
those JSON and maintain the state so I
am saying node is essentially giving you
that runtime and there are a variety of
frameworks in node.js which can help you
create this kind of you know variety of
MVC frameworks rather on node based
based on top of node oh sure okay so
that would be like angular a backbone oh
wow yeah so similar to like how you have
angular backbone on the front end on the
back end you have what I call as war em
based framework right which are
essentially doing a model driven
development so Express if you you know
Express write X play baby you could
maybe you could define for our what what
is Express okay so when node was written
think about load as your runtime
platform right it's it's about ten
thousand lines of code it's a set of
core libraries so the JavaScript
yovanovich Radian is the exactly and
what it runs on is the v8 container
right so what v8 does is v8 gives you
the ability to execute JavaScript but
below v8 there is a library called a
sleepy Yui which helps you translate you
know the JavaScript into your native
operations and then you have you know a
kernel layer you know which you are
pooling and talking natively right so
and that's where relax as a company
strongloop came into existence because
our code
portes who founded the company used to
maintain libuv
which was the Slayer below v8 right now
on top of it you know when you install
node you are getting ue you are getting
the vir distribution you are getting a
set of core models these are called node
core which and these are also have
middleware components oh I want to
connect with a back-end I need a set of
drivers oh I need to do basic network
operations HTTP server for example is
the first-class citizen so all these
libraries are what we call as the core
node distribution so to go to node.js
dot-org and download node that's what
you are getting okay as well as a set of
drivers based on your operating system
because you might be installing it on
Mac or Windows or UNIX so what you have
now on top of it to build any type of
realistic applications folks use
frameworks right so there are what we
call as a DIY or Do It Yourself
frameworks at the very basic these are
construction block level frameworks one
of the most popular or the widest
accepted one is called expressjs and
express was built on top of a middleware
call as Connect which helped me and it
almost evolved into an ecosystem and
like if you wanted to build a full stack
application like oh I wanted to connect
this to MongoDB I had a package called
as Mongoose a node packages were
packaged with in Express as an ecosystem
oh I wanted to do templating right then
you know you had packages like g8
handlebar moustache it had a lot of web
templating support or maybe if you
wanted to do authentication it had
support for passport jas which helped
you know plugged in into Active
Directory you ought to do a lot of token
validations and all so Express we went
on to became the most popular web
middleware framework and I would still
say 80 to 90 percent of today's node.js
applications are built on top of Express
it it's wrong to be recently took over
maintenance of Express six months back
so that's what we are doing from a
community perspective along with
maintaining node core also so let's talk
a bit about about the VA
so I guess you could start by talking
about exactly how how v8 has evolved and
how it enables node to evolve so you
know it all started with realistically
you will have to go back a little bit
earlier right in history so if you
looked at browser right there was
Netscape Navigator around 94 ish right
and they did not have JavaScript support
and later on they added JavaScript and
then I am JavaScript yeah the first
version of Netscape Navigator did not
have JavaScript support that would be
surprising that was way back in 94 like
but I think it was like they were soon
realized that now you need that right
and then very second I think it was like
a drop or like it was on the major
version release it came with JavaScript
support right this was way back in 94
and then you know ie came about you know
with 95 and they still did not have SSL
and so on right so but then you know by
that time you know javascript suppose
was was becoming kind of a requirement
and in 98 you know there wasn't even
Mozilla it there was something called a
sea monkey right there was an entire
application suite and this was based on
the original source code from the
Netscape Navigator right and then they
went on to create a web developer
communicator it was an entire
application composition package and
that's where you know JavaScript started
becoming a first-class citizen right
because people needed to develop in
JavaScript on the browser side and then
all of a sudden Firefox came in in 2004
late in the game it said oh let's make
this a little bit more lighter we don't
have to support VB script ActiveX but if
he wills you know support full stack
JavaScript that's fine
now when in 2008 that was one time
coincidentally chrome came for sorry
chrome was getting developed right as
based on the WebKit platform and this
WebKit platform was exactly the same as
Apple's Safari Browser platform okay so
they really did not invent it it was
more or less
however that being said when chrome
applications were written there was a
new OS getting form called as chromium
right and there were also like some
lacking support for some dotnet
utilities so v8 was actually not created
for node it was created for running
Chrome or chromium applications right as
well as you know supporting some dotnet
WCF calls
however you know then Ryan Dell
originally started the project and then
the he had help from other node core
contributors as well so there was a
small team right and these guys worked
at different companies and then what
happened is Louie was getting created
because chrome v8 could run JavaScript
right so what you needed was some way to
hook this up into the native system on
the server side so Bert and Ben with the
founders of strongloop they were working
on Libby we along with I think Fedor
from boxer right so there were two or
three major guys working on Libby Yui so
they started collaborating and it'll say
hey you know what this makes sense that
v8 should be ported over to the server
side and node can be support as a
container because not only can it just
render the browser but it can actually
now talk with the operating system it
can go do native calls it mean can do I
operate so I would say Libby we played a
major role along with you know the v8
container which was essentially you know
high-performance JavaScript right to put
it over to the server servers so that's
how I see the image so if you if you
need this this will probably illustrate
my misunderstanding something but if you
need v8 to run node and you don't have
v8 on you know if you're using Firefox
or if you're using Safari how do how do
you have alright maybe I maybe I'm
missing something like because you know
by understanding is
if v8 is specific to Chrome and I mean
we're so how do how do node based
applications work in the domain of
Firefox or Safari yeah so essentially
you know we when we talk about Firefox
or Safari you can't really run Firefox
or Safari on the server right you're
essentially running it on the client as
a browser right right right right now
chrome you know v8 was not needed for
chrome it was actually built for
chromium which was like they said okay
less can we actually port the browser
platform to run on the server side right
so this isn't really opening of web
pages for you but essentially doing
database calls right or maybe doing
memory calls writing to days calling
other services right so you are
essentially creating a runtime platform
similar to a JVM right so this was not
possible in JavaScript because first of
all you needed a container to run
JavaScript so people said oh can we put
Firefox right so just to specify a v8 is
written in C++ but it's not written in
JavaScript correctly yet itself is
written in C++ but it supports the
JavaScript runtime right and then libuv
takes care of the underlying native
operations for v8 but that's all C code
out there right this both these
platforms are written in C C++ even
libuv is not JavaScript okay so that
being said v8 is not your only choice
tomorrow think about it like on mozilla
have you heard about a platform called
spider-man yeah so you can actually you
can port over and run node in spider
monkey too right if spider monkey is put
it over to the server side so all of a
sudden you get a new platform have you
heard of Oracle's new platform colors
nash falls they've simply launched it it
will probably be good for our listeners
if you could expand a bit on on spider
monkey and the Oracle platform that
you're talking about also right so
spider monkey in a project has been
there it was a very similar initiative
just like v8
to you know create a little bit more not
factor but a richer implementation to
fall to letting you know the
browser-based or JavaScript based
applications do more you know network
related operations right and it was you
know you can actually run it on the
server side but it hasn't gone to a
place yet where you know it becomes like
a replacement for v8
however Oracle has invested very heavily
since the past four years and we at
strongloop they collaborated with us as
well because we weren't kind of beta
testing and helping them out in a way so
they had launched this Java a
lightweight Java Runtime platform or
strong Java sorry they run they launch a
JavaScript runtime platform which is
modeled after a Java runtime platform
but it's very lightweight and it
essentially is a similar implementation
as v8 but it will it can run on the JVM
right so if you look at v8 you
essentially are just running it natively
right you don't have to install anything
to run v8 however this new JavaScript
runtime engine is being called Nash horn
it's spelled as na SH o RN and it can be
deployed on Java 1.8 onwards JD case
right so it's a GRE sitting on than 1.8
plus JDK but essentially now it has
thrown open the doors for big-time
enterprise adoption because enterprises
are used to you know plodding JVM right
they are probably already on 1/6 or 1/7
as they go to 1/8 onwards they can
actually just implement download nastran
and run their node.js application within
national without actually depending on
v8 right so that's a very big
announcement that came in recently from
Oracle and they have also developed
their projects one of them is called
Avatar dot Jas you know these are like
SDKs that they're developing and very
similar to that iBM has
developed node SDK but these are
essentially for making IBM products or
Oracle products you know compatible with
node giving you hooks you know to access
let's say if you're running an IBM
solution a business map process
management application can you hook into
those with no jsapi right so they're
both of these companies are heavily
developing a API hooks using SDKs so
maybe you could give me some insight
into the future of like what what are
what does application development gonna
look like like what when are people
gonna choose to use the JVM versus using
node for example if you look at mobile
projects today or even IOT projects
those two right even in the IOT world
iBM has launched a big community project
called as node read/write and there are
a bunch of connectors out there put very
very targeted for IOT and they have also
started integrating with strong loops
loopback framework right because what we
tried to do at our company was we said
ok expresses all good let's build beyond
Express what drove Java it was not just
people don't write clean Java
applications they use frameworks they
use hibernate spring starts you know
variety of frameworks right no js' you
need enterprise-grade frameworks so you
will see like there's a framework we
maintain called as loop back dot IO
there are other frameworks like meteor
you might have heard about meteor right
and there are other frameworks like
sails Jas right these are I would say a
little bit more advanced frameworks they
have ORM capabilities where you can you
know have a variety of back-end data
sources just like any app server you can
connect to these data sources you can
have modeling you can do relationship
mapping customization you can manage
connection pools you can do API
conversion well what I find interesting
is it sounds like what you're saying the
motivation for moving in the direction
of of node as opposed to the JVM is
basically you don't care about speed you
care about compatibility I would say two
things right you do
why how widely can you integrate in so
there are three use cases one is
integration third is when you say speed
I take it like it's like a superficial
world because if you look at one of the
use cases that EPA eBay and PayPal did
it was reducing the amount of code you
needed to write right so there's from
there and number of developers you
needed to write this on so it was more
about the productivity 50% productivity
increase for them so you yeah you you
you were talking about emphasizing
development speed over transaction speed
yes but again that being said there is a
third use case if you look at Groupon or
the implement they have you know their
use case was mostly performance driven
right and Nordic for them was like hey
if I do you know fad if I have writing
you know these fad web services in
legacy Java or.net I won't be able to
give the same amount of performance to
my mobile clients and if I light write
these API is in node or this apps in
node then obviously performance you know
is at least 5x better for me and even if
you look at you know all the real time
industry right we eat gaming
transportation IOT they are strictly
investing in node just for the
performance the high speed really even
what about like like high-frequency
trading I mean this is a very very
interesting so that's we should when we
are talking the greatness of node let's
talk about a little bit you know what's
lacking line all right so you'd be
surprised there are companies like Dow
Jones who have invested for years and I
would say 30 percent of their
application stack is not move just like
what
Ria's correct absolutely correct we are
talking with big financial institutions
now there are certain problems we still
need to solve right like what is not
lacking in oh this is all the
asynchronous thing is cool and you know
we can go deeper when we talk about
error management on all but transaction
management or transaction rollback or
transaction integrity these are not very
mature in node yet
right there have been attempts at doing
this using you know promises or trying
to include you know some kind of green
threads right meteor try to introduce
green threads to achieve you know
transaction management right but in the
node the normal load land you know
meteor is a very custom framework I
would say built on top of node they had
to implement their own models one of
them was called as node fiber but in
just the node lands their variety of
libraries which are trying to help
achieve this transaction management so
that's one area where node needs a
little bit more developing right before
everybody can bet like online wire
transfers or mode right because hey what
happens if that wire transfer fails can
you actually roll it back can you audit
it right that needs then end-to-end
transactions stitching and it's very
difficult to do in a synchronous code
where you don't have a context of a
thread local like you would have in Java
or.net or any other thread basically
yeah so I guess let's let's talk a
little bit about the penalties of being
in JavaScript world so there's the
classic complained about callback hell
could you maybe illustrate callback hell
and talk about how that plays into node
or how node is able to work against that
yeah so if you look at callback hell
what's what's really happening right if
you were doing a synchronous processing
right let's take a very simple example
I'm trying to call like read a file with
it from this rate I'll say okay start
reading this file and I'm probably done
and you know when I'm done in the
synchronous line I don't care right
because I'm waiting for the thread
however in the JavaScript land what I
want to do is invoke that function and I
want to when that function is complete I
want to send you a contact right simple
but it isn't so simple because that file
operation could also throw me an error
right and that error I want to handle
that as in another callback right
however if the operation completes
properly then I have the final callback
so now I have a nested callback right
now that pattern can you know start
becoming more and more complicated as I
go into the implementation side of it
right and all of a sudden when you know
you are trying to say okay I might have
like five nested callbacks and maybe one
of them threw a error right because each
of these requests the execution request
and the callback they are a process of
separate event loop events right on
dates there is no effective way that you
know if some error happens that you can
do a staggered you know long stack trace
right and figure it out exactly which
callback you know through that error and
maybe how do you remedy that error so
this causes a lot of pain while really
debugging and tracing for errors in
application and this is where you know
it's also term as callback hell you have
callbacks within callbacks within
callbacks and so on try figuring it out
right so there are certain libraries
which took a at them to you know solve
this problem one of them was call as
promised right there was a promise
library so you could promise if I your
function right it had things like okay
that the basic instructor level it had
like two functions right one was like oh
you fulfill your promise you reject a
promise and then you know while that
promise is getting executed that's
called the runtime of that promise right
so if you say hey read a file and in
that you know I'll say okay read file
and you know I'll return a new promise
and within that I'll say you know if I
have an error I essentially that promise
will give me a rejection if I don't get
that error then I assume that it's a
fulfilled function right now what you
can do here is you can now implement a
try-catch block will with this right so
you can say hey create a new promise
within the try block block you know you
are essentially doing fulfillment and if
the try block fails you are catching a
particular day exception but when you do
that exception you know you are
essentially rejecting it so you are
setting the state of that promised block
as failed state right and then you can
every handleerror around this okay and
you can even change this right so
instead of fulfilling or reject this
there are like simple verbs which help
you do this so there is something like
you know when the promise completes
normally you see say that it's has a
method called as API call has got done
but instead of dot done you could simply
say it dot then right so you can say
read file right then function return the
callback so only when you know your
function is complete then you can have
like all these nested blocks which are
defined like if you are going through a
loop you can say dot for each you can
have like you know dot done or dot map
or you know use dot then you know you
have all these verbs which make your
life easier you say used to be a Java
programmer
how does programming in node compare to
programming in Java oh it's a pain and
that's where you know I was giving you
this simple example why you know promise
to connect tempt at this
but promise did not really solve all of
this for me right because think about it
in the Java world I just had to do a try
a catch and finally write and I did not
have to care about how the thread is
managed okay
the thread execution went through my
trike block got an exception it got
caught and at the end of the execution
school my finally gets in go goes and
click okay but I'm sorry is it a pain
because you're not used to it or is it a
pain because like it's fundamentally
just feels worse no I think it's both
one is not used to it but again like I
have added like over taking the headache
I have to go and implement libraries
explicitly to do what we call a thread
tracking or it me as tracking in my code
which I don't have to write in Java for
example that the the platform takes care
of itself so there are other ones I
would like to specify not just promises
this is one thing that we are working
from the core perspective it's library
call as soon so that's gonna I think
change the node.js land forever zone is
essentially introducing
thread-local into node.js Oh interesting
so by default we can zone if I express
so you won't even know about that right
you can just use unified Express and you
ex use Express exactly the same way but
there is a root zone you know so it's a
library which you require and the root
zone gives you an execution it basically
gives you a wrapper around the execution
scope okay and then you have these
functions which are called child zones
and you have similarly a try-catch and a
return block and when you are exit
exiting the scope of the function the
return bog block gets called it goes and
cleans up resources exactly the same way
as a finally block used to do in Java
right so if you have event emitters and
all those those get cleaned up and a
meanwhile if you throw an error it does
not go and crash your application that
error is captured and it just sets the
state of that zone as a failed state and
zone itself has proper error handling
mechanism it will not go and you know
just crash your application with an
unhandled exception okay where can
people go to find out more about node or
to find out more about you yeah so we
have like a few ones so we maintain
Express jeaious you know if you are
starting at the you know construction
blocks start there if you go to Express
J's comm you know we have all the
documentation specs libraries as well we
do maintain loopback dot IO that's the
web page which was and this is linked
from Express web page as well I would
say this is mint mint as the enterprise
ready frameworks open source frameworks
built on top of Express we do create we
are known for technical blogs and
articles we have online study guides we
recommend the best ones we haven't
written all of them we recommend the
best ones from the community so we have
sort you know create a curated that
content plus our blogs are like you know
people are some companies are known for
doling out t-shirts we are known for
doling out technical blogs we have 300
class great technical blogs and white
papers written on the strong side for
the community the
you know discussing all these different
aspects right both from runtime as well
as the depth time imposition perspective
and how can people learn more about you
well or contact you yeah if they can you
know if you want to send a note that you
know call back at strongloop comm right
you can go to our website as well but I
think you know of just in the community
we n our handle is also called call back
at strong lucam that way to get in touch
with us that's very funny
great all right well Schubert car thank
you so much for coming on software
engineering radio it's really been a
pleasure talking to you no thank you
it's been really my pleasure you know
speaking with you and thanks for
inviting you know my goal and my wish
here it really is that note becomes a
mainstream technology so I we already
see the huge adoption curve but it
becomes mainstream in the next year or
so
interesting okay that's great well well
I'll talk to you soon shubra all right
thanks okay all right I'll see ya thanks
for listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to support us you can advertise se
radio by clicking the Digg reddit
delicious or slash buttons on the site
or by talking about this on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]